Some of you guys may know me.
I run my mouth on Twitter because I have adult ADHD
and that's just exactly my drug of choice.
I'm now hanging out on Mastodon,
but I haven't left Twitter either.
So you guys may know me from kind of either place.
More importantly than me running my mouth too much
and having been around data stuff for a while is in,
in, let's see, I would have, I was born in 1972.
So Christmas of 1980, I was eight years old
and stuck under my bed in the place
that would later hold Victoria's Secret catalogs
was actually stuck at that point in my life,
the Lego catalog.
And the Lego catalog was dog-eared
and this was the Lego kit that 1980 version of me
wanted more than any,
this was my Red Ryder BB gun of 1980.
And in Christmas morning, 1980,
I came downstairs and Santa Claus had brought this Lego kit
and it was the apex Lego experience of my life.
And I'm not even sure if my parents know this,
but I'll make sure they watch this video and know this.
And actually my only regret was every other Christmas
for the rest of my life has been somewhat
of a disappointment compared to getting this kit
with the actual motor and it changed gears
and it even went in reverse.
And I was eight years old, right?
So by the time I got in middle school
and taking physics class,
I thought that the people who thought the engine spun
in the other direction when you put it in reverse,
I thought they were brain damaged
because that was beyond intuitive to me
because I had been building actual little transmissions
with gears since I was eight years old.
Anyway, I mentioned Lego and Lego being the apex toy
because much to my pleasant surprise,
last year in Nature Magazine,
Adam Converse, Hales and Klotz had a paper
that had a Lego example.
They did actual work with humans
and it had a Lego problem in the middle of it.
So I'm immediately interested
because we know Lego are the apex toy.
So in their paper, they gave participants in a study
the Lego arrangement you see on the left.
Actually, it wasn't a Lego minifigure.
They had a Star Wars character
and I'll show it to you in a minute in the next slide.
When it got published for copyright reasons,
they couldn't put the Star Wars Stormtrooper in there.
So I think actually in the, I got the paper right here.
I think they do just a little drawing
with figurine removed.
But anyway, it looked like the thing on the left.
And what they asked participants first, yeah,
they don't even have the figurine in here.
It's just a placeholder.
What they asked participants to do is said,
okay, take this Lego model
and make it so that we can put this brick
on top of that top part
and it not crush the figurine.
That was the first challenge they gave folks.
And so you can imagine,
and you guys should do this in your head.
Imagine you've got these blocks, you've got this figurine,
you've got this Lego arrangement.
How do you arrange this so you can put the block on,
or sorry, the brick on top of the Lego blocks
and not crush the figurine?
All right, so think about that.
And that's actually how it looked in real life.
So like the next cycle of this,
they say, okay, we're gonna give you a dollar
to solve this problem,
but each additional block costs 10 cents
and it's gotta hold this brick on top.
So think about how you might solve that.
All right, so you might put three more blocks on there.
You'll be down 30 cents, still make 70 cents, right?
There's other ways you might've solved.
You might try to put just one in the corner
and hope they put the brick on really square
so it balances.
Anyway, they also in a third round prompted people
with just the phrase, removing a block has no cost.
Now think about this yourself.
How would you have solved this Lego problem
if I prompt you with removing a block has no cost?
Now, I wish I could see the whole audience.
If you're in the chat over here,
I've got the general tab open.
Let me know if you changed your mind
when I said removing a block has no cost
because a huge number of respondents in this study did
because the default action
was to think about adding something.
And they discovered that it was only through prompting
and they had to do pretty strong prompts.
They could get people to think about removing
and people would see it.
And then they would begin to choose subtracting.
And it was kind of like the big surprise
of this whole paper is additive ideas come to mind quickly
and easily, but subtractive ideas
require more cognitive effort.
So they decided to test this with a bunch of stuff
that boringly weren't Lego blocks.
I don't know why,
but they tested it with things like recipes.
So if we give people a recipe and say,
how do you make this better?
Almost nobody removed something from the recipe.
What they do is they add something.
The exception to that is if they had something ridiculous
in the recipe that folks will be like,
oh, right, yeah, remove that.
That doesn't belong, you know,
something savory doesn't belong in the dessert, right?
Like it would be better if you subtracted that.
But outside of kind of the ridiculous,
people don't see subtracting something for a recipe
as a way to get it better.
And trust me, every recipe that I have ever made
that I got offline, after I made it,
I'm like half this crap, we don't need it.
And we can simplify it dramatically
by just like not doing all these steps.
It's almost like they think people won't enjoy it
if they don't do a lot of complicated steps.
Similarly, the study took that this nation
that mentioned in this nature paper,
they took a bunch of vacation plans
and put them in front of people
and said, make these vacation plans better.
And most folks default is to add an activity.
Now, my wife and I would have had that tendency
and we had a kid who is now 15 and we later learned,
you know, we have a lot more fun
if we try to do one thing in the morning
and maybe one thing in the afternoon,
but make the thing in the afternoon, like optional,
so that like no charge to cancel,
so that we can punch out if things start going bad.
Like that's how we discovered how to have happy holidays
and good vacations.
But if you give people just an agenda,
they will try to shove more stuff into it.
And it's because this is human nature,
which as I looked around and thought about it,
I realized I see this kind of everywhere.
And this is a little bit like getting a new car
of a certain type.
You will begin to see these everywhere.
Once I have primed you for subtractive thinking is hard
and people don't tend to do it,
you will begin to see this everywhere.
So that's my Santa gift to you all
is introducing this idea of subtractive thinking
and allowing you to see how hard it is,
but that there's great benefit.
So let's look at a few examples,
other things where subtractive thinking comes in play.
Or as my 15 year old daughter says,
cool story, bro, but why do we care?
Well, we have already seen mention
of this minimum viable product diagram,
at least in the chat.
I don't know if it made it into one of the presentations,
but for those of you who haven't seen it,
the general idea is if you design products,
it are incrementally where they aren't useful
until you get to the very end,
basically your customers are unhappy with you
the whole time until the very end,
except the reality we all know is at step four,
they look at you because that was not what they wanted.
So actually it doesn't even work this way.
This is like a stylized positive version.
The real way is, or I'm sorry,
the MVP way that Henrik Kynberg recommends
in his, what is Scrum is this thing that's become iconic,
where you give somebody a skateboard
and it's not super happy,
but you give them a little bit more
and it kind of becomes useful.
And iteratively, we add a couple more features
and we get iteratively more useful,
but they don't hate it all the way through.
Well, what is this exercise other than reducing down
what is the minimum thing we can give somebody
that they get positive utility from?
I just slipped into economics talk,
but that they're somewhat happy with,
what is the minimum thing we can give them?
And then we ask, what is the next marginal improvement?
Oh my God, I did it again.
What is the next marginal improvement
that we can make on this thing
to make it a little bit more useful?
Okay, so this is this exercise
in reductive subtractive thinking,
where we are trying to figure out
what's the least we can do to make the most positive value.
So the whole minimum viable product exercise
is really just to try to trick your brain
into subtractive thinking.
Some of you may see,
I gave a presentation some years ago on empathy
and I presented the thesis that in Agile, the user story,
what that really is, is a hack
to get you to be empathetic with a specific user, right?
But we make it a specific user,
we narrow down what it is we're talking about.
And we introduce this hack of the user story
and it forces empathy.
It becomes a forcing function for empathy
in the mind of a software developer.
I think the minimum viable product
is a forcing function for reductive thinking
that we interject into our development processes
in order to prime and pump us
for this effective way of thinking, which is reductive.
When what our brains kind of want to do is be additive.
So it's a subtractive prompt.
And remember from our first part of this presentation,
prompting is incredibly important
because we're actually open to subtractive thinking.
We're not morally opposed to it.
It's just not like our default mind state.
And so having prompts is super useful.
And I think that's why the MVP,
part of why the MVP model has gotten so highly adopted
is it's effective because we're responsive to prompts.
All right, so let's think about more reductive things.
A few of you may have seen my comment online
where I talk about reading through an answer
on Stack Overflow, and please ignore my spelling errors.
And I thought, wow, that's a really great answer.
And I really learned some things
and I got down to the bottom
and I discovered it was my answer
that I wrote eight years ago.
All right, so besides being kind of comically silly
that I would read something I wrote
and not even recognize it as my own writing,
the one of the things that this reminded me of
is the way I ended up writing so much on Stack Overflow
was that I just happened to be there when it started.
And I was just learning R as Stack Overflow was starting.
And one of the things a handful of us did,
and actually, Chris, I had forgotten
you were involved in this
because I found notes relatively recently.
And I had completely forgotten, I didn't know you then.
And by the way, long-time listener, first-time caller,
this is the first time Chris and I
have ever talked in real voice,
although we have traded messages on and off
over the last years and years.
But Chris was there, Mike Driscoll,
who's with RealData, RealR-I-L-L-Data,
and they just launched product this week.
Mike Driscoll and I helped prime Stack Overflow
with R questions because there weren't many R questions,
and we felt like the R discussion list online,
the email list, was not super helpful for learners.
And so we got a bunch of questions
that had been asked on other R discussion forums
and things that had been put into a search engine
of a popular R site,
and we turned them into questions for Stack Overflow.
And then we just divided it up.
A bunch of people posted questions,
a bunch of people answered questions,
and we seeded the R tag on Stack Overflow.
So I was sort of there at the beginning in a bunch of ways,
and I haven't answered or asked
a Stack Overflow question in years,
but I was real active early on.
And one of the things I did
is every time I was learning something,
it was R, then later it was Pandas,
as I began to use more Python as Pandas came on.
And I started to ask more questions,
and I had developed the skill of reducing
my thinking and my question
down to something fairly specific.
And that allowed me to answer a good question
that could be answered.
And over time, this got a name.
This began to be called a reprex,
or a reproducible example,
and began to be called that.
And as a matter of fact, Jenny Bryan,
who did one of the lightning talks about naming things,
Jenny Bryan has a library for R called reprex
for helping make these easier to make.
Reprexes are an exercise in reductive thinking.
They're unreasonably effective
because when you write a reprex,
it's a type of debugging.
If you have a problem
and you're writing a reproducible example,
it is akin to rubber duck debugging
in that the process of reducing your question down
to a minimum viable example,
you actually a lot of times,
well, I actually a lot of times,
discover what I was doing wrong or what the problem is
before I ever answer the question,
because I get all the noise
of everything else I was working on out of the way,
and I get down to the brass tacks of what the problem is,
and then I'm like, oh, dumbass, there it is.
And it just jumps out at me.
Now, sometimes it doesn't,
and I'm able to share it online on Stack Overflow
with my team in a Slack, wherever,
and somebody else can just copy, paste it
into their editor, run it,
and be like, oh, dude, here you go.
Here's what's going on.
And like, oh, I see now that matrix was shaped
the opposite of what I thought it was or whatever.
So you can get more eyes on the problem quickly
because you allow someone else
to understand your problem more quickly.
That's reductive to get there, and it's hard.
It's gotta be explicitly taught, right?
When analysts come in and start working with us,
they often sit down with me with a problem
that is too complicated for me
to understand what they're doing,
and they're a little surprised
because they've got this whole course of knowledge problem.
They understand what's going on on the screen.
They can't believe that I can't
because I'm smarter than them from their point of view.
I should be able to understand it.
And so I always give them as a challenge,
hey, let's do this as an exercise first
in reducing and focusing your question down
and creating a reprex.
So I'm a huge fan of reprexes
as a type of reductive thinking.
Now, I'd went through this exercise recently with Coiled,
who they're a company that supports
and employs a number of Dask contributors.
And I had a Dask problem that wasn't working well.
We actually hired them to come in where I work
and partner with us and work on a problem we had.
And I've shared this story elsewhere,
but at the end of it, they said,
hey, this was kind of an interesting problem
and showed a limitation or a challenge in Dask
because it was a big, like unbalanced join,
and it was a mini to mini join.
It was just gnarly behaved problem.
It just didn't flow well through anything.
And they're like, hey, can we have your data,
like anonymize it more and let's use it?
And I said, actually, no, but I can make dummy data
that acts, I think I understand this problem enough
to make dummy data that acts like this real data.
And I just went in and worked with them and we created,
and this is all public on GitHub,
we created a reproducible example of this dummy dataset
that's got 4 billion records.
Now, this is an awful lot,
what Julia Silgi talked about
with making simulated data to learn something.
Well, I made simulated data to match a real problem,
but I did it because I could make it public.
And then we could use that as a test
against different distributed platforms.
I mean, Coiled can use it against Dask.
Somebody else may wanna play with it against Spark
to make Spark better.
Great, everybody wins, right?
It's a certain class of challenging problem.
But that is a type of reductive thinking.
We had to go through the process of figuring out
what was it about my problem that made it difficult or hard?
And then we had to reproduce that.
That was largely a reductive exercise.
It wasn't this, it wasn't that,
it's only these facets of the problem.
And then we created simulated data
to represent those parts of the problem at scale.
Super useful.
So I'm a big fan of Adam Savage.
And what could be more norm core
than every tool is a hammer?
I kind of psychologically made my way through COVID
by laying underneath an old Jeep,
getting various motor fluids in my face.
And part of the time I was doing this,
I was listening to Adam Savage's book.
And one of the things that really jumped out at me
in the book is he talks about buying material
to build everything he builds three times.
So he goes into a build
knowing he's gonna build it three times.
The first time you work the kinks out
and you just sort of figure out how it works.
The second time you get a really good version,
but it isn't camera perfect.
And he makes props for movies, so it has to be camera perfect.
So after the second time,
he then knows enough to build it the third time
and get it camera perfect.
And I think this is part of a reductive thinking
is not planning the first time we do something
to boil the ocean.
And that was mentioned in the presentation right before me
about not trying to do everything.
Like just get your logic flowing through a system
and then figure out where your performance bottlenecks are.
That's a certain type of reductive thinking.
So to repeat myself,
subtractive or reductive thinking is not our default.
It's hard.
Prompting to think subtractive helps considerably.
We can be prompted.
MVPs are a great prompt to think about reducing
or subtracting things.
Reproducible examples are a critical meta skill
that are reductive.
Refactor for simplicity,
reduce it down is a really good use case
of subtractive thinking.
And even taking out code and using a library
that someone else maintains,
that's even subtractive thinking.
So on that note, I had listed some job openings.
They're also in the chat, in the Slack.
So let me stop sharing and we'll do Q&A.