I am going to talk a little bit about my experience
about being sort of staff citizen
or a senior engineer at Twitter and how my job changed.
So a little bit about me,
I, you know, in a previous life,
I had a PhD in math after some soul searching
or life crisis as some other people might call it.
I did what many people in that situation would do,
which is go to find a software job.
After a few years, I moved to San Francisco
to do data science for a conversion and ad company.
And in the past five and a half years ago,
I have been at Twitter where I co-founded
the Machine Learning Ethics Transparency
and Accountability Team.
And I operated as a capacity of tech lead
for a research lead for the team.
And sort of like this talk really came,
I started thinking more about leadership for ICs
during my time at Twitter.
And so maybe if there is one thing that I want you
to remember in the spirit of this conference is this name.
So we'll, it's a little bit more nuanced than this,
but when people talk about a manager in an IC
sort of career, they are presented usually very separately.
However, what I'm hoping to convince you
is that they're actually not as different
as people claim them to be.
So maybe let me start with some disclaimers.
This is not a talk about what being a staff plus IC mean.
There has been books and blogs
and many other resources being about that.
So this is not about that.
This is also not a talk to convince you to be an IC
or not to be an IC, or if you should be a manager
or you should not be a manager.
I don't have anything against manager.
Manager are awesome.
Having a great manager really helps.
Of course, there are not everyone is a great manager,
but that's true for everyone.
And so, I have talked about, I've used these words,
like IC is geriatric IC, like what does the word mean?
So let's start maybe by defining them.
So IC is short for individual contributor,
is someone who in, usually in tech companies
is a person who might ship code or do analysis.
Roughly speaking, we can think as someone
who consumes your stories.
For the purpose of this talk,
we'll consider a geriatric IC or senior citizen,
someone who is equal or above,
of course, that depends on the role
and the company senior level.
And sometimes these roles are called staff or principal
and senior level in most companies consider
sort of like to be the final level,
meaning that if you want, you can stay at that level
without sort of getting flagged for performance,
lack of performance.
A manager, as we might know,
but I just wanna make it clear,
is someone who manages people, has like little direct reports
and so usually is responsible for the team.
Of course, it's not always like,
there is a lot of gray areas in between the two.
Some companies also allow
what is usually called tech lead manager,
but for the sake of this talk and for simplicity,
we are going to ignore this for now.
And so what is the latter?
The latter is usually the process that,
you know, is in companies to get promoted.
And so as I was mentioning earlier in my introduction,
like my time really at Twitter made me think
a little bit more about all this leadership
and like how, like sort of like a career for IC
is not that different for manager in the sense that,
so I was promoted to staff a couple of years ago.
My job really changed drastically.
However, I did not receive any proper or specific training
for that.
And so what really, what happened to me,
it was, you know, I was trying to do my work
and then someone would say like,
oh, you should join this planning meeting.
Or, you know, I was added to a bunch of other meetings
and at the same time, I was still being asked
to keep contributing, to keep being INC,
like to ship my own code, to ship my own analysis.
And at first I was very confused and annoyed
and I would like begrudgingly join all these meetings.
In fact, here's a picture of me in this meetings.
And again, like not really understanding
why I was being asked to do too many jobs at the same time.
Over time, I realized that I was juggling multiple things
and maybe that is what the job is all about.
And so I was not only doing IC work for myself.
So like, again, pushing code in my case, doing analysis.
I was also mentoring junior people from my team, you know,
meaning helping them with the day-to-day sort of jobs
and should we do X or Y?
How do we interpret this analysis?
How do we frame this problem?
A lot of that.
And also people from other teams,
maybe more on the monthly basis or so.
But I was also involved in a lot of this sort of like
planning, team strategy, high-level meetings,
a lot of talking that I was not expecting at first.
And you know, oftentimes when the discussion of like,
should you be a manager?
Should you stay as an IC?
Should you be a team leader?
And so when these questions and ideas
and ideas and ideas and ideas come out,
I feel there is a lot of themes that keep coming back
and that I might disagree with.
So for example, I hear a lot, you know,
I want to remain on the C ladder
because I don't like meetings.
Or, you know, I don't like talking to people.
I don't like being interviewed.
So I think all of those are sort of like things
that I've seen and heard multiple times in conversation
when people were sort of deciding to be,
maybe to switch to management.
However, my friend Nick said that the best,
in the best way possible,
which is any simplicity advanced engineer
is indistinguishable from management.
It's a little bit of an exaggeration,
but is what the entire sort of like idea
behind this talk is.
So let's talk for a moment about ladders,
tech ladders, or how do you get promoted in a big company?
So here's an example of what, you know,
a data science ladder, for example,
could look like in your company.
So, you know, you have a couple of entry levels,
then you might get to like senior level.
And then there is a bunch of other things after senior.
Again, they might be called staff,
they might be called something else.
There might be, you know, here is a seven step ladder.
It might be a different number of levels in your company,
but it doesn't matter.
The point being, there is usually sort of like that level,
which in here, we identify between sort of like senior
and staff where the job really changes.
And that's where we call it geriatric,
as we defined earlier.
Sometimes, you know, some people might decide
that they want to actually do management.
And usually that happens not before someone reaches
sort of like the senior level of IC,
and they say, I would like to be a manager.
And the company says like, great, let me train you.
Let me give you some training for that.
And they would receive manager training and, you know,
be a manager.
On top of that, the more they go up their ladder,
they will have even more training.
Sometimes fancy school will do adult programs
for director plus or VP level.
And of course, this is absolutely not a complaint
about manager receiving training.
I do think, and I do hope people, you know,
companies will keep trained manager.
They are very important.
However, my question is what happens,
what do we get as ICs when we go up on our ladder?
We don't really get anything.
And so the point here in a maybe more visual way
is that the two ladders are not really parallel
as people tend to, as people like to think,
but they actually tend to collide.
And, you know, I know what you're asking now,
like, did I do this terrible slide myself?
Yes, thank you.
As you may know, graphic design is indeed my passion.
And so, you know, this is, it is something
that I have seen many people struggle in,
like at that level, when they not tend to be aware
of sort of like the leadership part.
Sometimes people tend to think that in order for them
to grow to the ladder, to be promoted to all the levels,
they just have to be sort of like more hardcore,
whatever that means.
However, this is not enough.
In fact, this is probably not the most important part.
So let's talk about skill sets.
What better way than talking about skill set
than Venn diagram?
In fact, you know, like Kamala, I do a lot of Venn diagrams
as well.
I said before, usually skill set are presented
very, in a very complimentary ways.
So, you know, you have manager skills
and then you have sort of like drag or IC skills
and, you know, they don't really touch.
Some example that, you know, we heard a lot is like,
oh, you're good at talking with people.
You should consider being a manager or maybe a PM.
However, I think, again, as I mentioned earlier,
I think this is a lie because after a certain threshold,
and again, that's where the dragic part comes in,
they really overlap a lot.
And so I do think that the real picture
is not to, it's not to non-overlapping Venn diagram,
but it's something like closer to this.
And of course there are some skills that are, you know,
IC only or manager only.
So for example, you know, as an IC,
you're indeed expected to, you know, publish your own code,
being opinionated about any kind of technical decision,
write technical design docs and whatnot.
As a manager, of course, you're, you know,
supposed to do a salary conversation with your reports.
You're supposed to honestly have a lot
of awkward conversation,
do a bunch of admin stuff and whatnot.
However, my point here is that the stuff that really matters
is not the stuff that it's on the border,
but it's stuff that's in the middle.
And that's what I see mostly tend to lack
because we lack training.
And so let's call this the make shit happen skills.
And so if we look at this, at this like area of overlap,
we see there is a lot of things that are classically
not associated with IC work, right?
So there is mentoring, for example, as I mentioned earlier,
like literally checking with more junior people
on a almost daily basis if needed,
if they're blocked, if they need help, a lot of meetings.
Some of this meeting might be about planning.
Some other meetings might be, you know, with other teams.
Indirect impact, so like, how do we make stuff happen
that I cannot do it myself because of lack of time?
And, you know, a big project honestly required a lot of people
and so a single person cannot and should not,
this is actually an anti-pattern, I think,
if a single person does everything by themselves.
And so what is it, you know,
what does it convincing people to do stuff mean?
Well, maybe it's, you know, you have an idea
and you want to get headcount for that.
In fact, our political amplification work
started exactly that way.
Like a simple idea, having a prototype
and then trying to get a larger team to work on that.
Maybe it's getting technical consensus
for a critical decision, or maybe it's helping,
you know, unblock someone on my team
to work with some other team.
Maybe there's an issue there
and they're not understanding each other.
Is there something we can do there?
Or maybe, you know, it was to convince other teams
that we should work together on a single issue.
And so honestly, these, you know, in my work,
this came out a lot because my team
did not own any of the models.
And so if you really wanted to have any kind of an impact
in the product, we had to convince other people
who owned the model themselves to,
to make the changes.
So that's where the indirect impact comes from.
And so this is sort of, again,
this is, this middle area is like the area that mostly,
talking to people is the part that is most invulnerable,
right?
And not doing code yourself,
but making sure that other people are enabled to do,
to do their work.
In fact, I would even argue that the technical work
is the easy part.
The people work is the hard part.
Sometimes teams have conflicting priorities.
How do you convince them that they should listen to you
instead of maybe their own priorities?
I do think that this is, you know,
like as I mentioned, like the people work
is really the hard part here.
And so what's the difference really?
You know, what do manager do maybe that we don't as I see?
You know, capitalism, like the military requires
a very strong hierarchical structure
where there can only be one person formally in charge.
And in companies, this is usually the manager.
And so usually they have internal responsibility
for the team.
And this goes both ways, right?
If something goes wrong,
they are the first one getting yelled.
And of course they will be able,
they will then try to figure out
what was wrong in the team.
At the same time, if you know, everything is great,
the manager will be the one sort of like represented
in the team for the phrases.
And of course, great manager will be able
to elevate their reports as well.
I mentioned that earlier, but I wanna say that again,
like part of a manager job is also to have a bunch
of awkward conversation.
Not everyone likes it.
And finally, you know, if you really want to sort of like
be a C-level person in a company,
eventually, if you eventually want to be a C-level person
in a company, most often all the path
involves the manager chain.
And so what I was thinking about this talk, I was like,
well, you know, what is that I've learned in my last,
you know, a few years in my career that really helped me?
What is like the sort of like a really important thing
I learned?
And I don't think it's anything related
to a specific technology, a specific library
or a specific whatever, but it's really like
the social skills that I learned in my career
and it's really like the social skills that I learned
just by doing this work.
And so, you know, the real transferable skills
are the friends or the social skills we made along the way.
And so to conclude and recap,
I wanna say that, you know,
manager usually get leadership training
when they start being managers.
However, I see don't even after they sort of like
pass a threshold that we call geriatric.
Their work is very similar to management.
So why don't we get the same training?
I think as an industry, we should be more aware of that.
And, you know, especially because this is holding
many folks back because no one told people
that that is something that's really important.
And so that resonates with you.
And if you're interested,
I've left some ways of keeping in touch.